24 hours for these competitors.
32 divers set out in hope at 7 o'clock last night.
Now we're down to the best 12 after this morning's semi-final reduced the number down from 18.
With defending champion Matthew Mitchum without doubt the big name to miss out on tonight's final when he finished an agonising 13th.
Another packed house here in the Aquatic Centre as they're introduced to the finalists here.
The majority, of course, will be noisily rooting for the British home favourite, the poster boy for these London 2012 Games, who finished fourth in the semis with his confidence and his performance building steadily.
Terrific mood all over Olympic Park.
This evening, as two amazing weeks starts to reach its conclusion,
Get ready to hear those home supporters.
Here is Tom Daley.
It's been a great game for Great Britain, but this young man, just 18 years of age, carries so many hopes on his young shoulders.
He's got his fan club out in force tonight.
Well, will he be inhibited or will he be inspired?
David Budai, the American next to him, enjoying the occasion and reveling in the atmosphere.
That's great to see.
But those supporters will know that it's the Chinese duo of Lin Yu here and Chubo next to him who've been setting the standards right from the off as they chase their country's seventh diving gold medal of the Games.
Here's Chubo.
leading after the semi-finals and the favourite for gold.
For six of those 12 finalists, the Olympic Games is a new experience.
Unlike for Steve Rebiliad sitting next to me, Steve, you've been studying the scores over the two rounds so far.
I mean, how much has the standard just built as this competition has progressed?
I think it's really significant, Roger, that from the men in the top 12 who've qualified for this final,
The lowest dive score in the semi was 72 and that from Riley McCormick and even that scored eights but with a low tariff so the consistency's really been building.
In the preliminaries we saw dives in the 30s and even a couple in the 20s.
The lift in consistency for the second phase of the competition was remarkable and now what we're looking for is consistency with high quality and that's what we're seeing from Chu and Lin and it's hard to see them being displaced from the top two positions
You wouldn't say right from the off that it's a battle for the bronze, but I think a few people might be thinking that.
Yes, in diving you cannot afford to make one mistake.
There's no three attempts as there is in the high jump or the long jump.
It's one strike and you're out, really.
judges being introduced they've got the toughest job of a lot in here as this standard builds in the competition.
Seven of them have to judge the execution of each dive which is of course is pre-announced and given a specific degree of difficulty or tariff.
You'll be able to follow this quite simply when the captions after each diver is put on your screen for you.
The top two and the bottom two marks are discounted and those three remaining marks are then multiplied by that degree of difficulty.
and the basic rule is that the higher the degree of difficulty the bigger the prize certainly with the lower degrees of difficulties you've got to execute them near perfectly to make sure you maintain the sort of point score you'll need to and it's very interesting to see Steve as it goes through the order they go in a one or two of them coming out playing their big dives early on hoping to
post a good score and one or two others starting a bit more conservatively.
And I just think that's a matter of courses for courses.
If it suits you to put in a tough dive early because you feel focused at the beginning of competition, do it then.
We saw some divers
struggle towards the end of the preliminaries it was such a long session that their legs were weary they admitted as much and and three of the top six i think had their worst dive as their sixth well they've had a good break in the middle of the day today plenty of talk about the short turnaround from last night to this morning but they should be well rested now and we're expecting them to perform at their best and they'll hope to do that
It was a three-hour session last night to reduce the numbers from thirty-two.
Couple of hours in the pool this morning.
They've had a good rest.
They were finished around about midday.
So, they've had a good eight hours or so back to the village, a rest.
Try to get the mind straight and then back here.
They've been warming up of course and now it is for real.
Six dives each.
Riley McCormick
And for many of these divers, the place in the final was their first aim.
And now it's all about what they can produce on the day.
Riley opening up with a forward three and a half somersault piked.
Pretty solid opening from him.
At 72, we talked about as being the lowest score from the top 12 was his opening dive.
And because it's got a low tariff, even these eights can't get him much above low to mid-70s.
There we go, 76.5, four points.
He's picked up there from the semifinal with the same guy.
right at the top of the scale.
They will be hitting three figures with a points total.
So, you're really looking to be in the 80s to low 90s to keep those medal chances going.
Next, Alexander Bondar from the Ukraine.
In with three and a half somersault three point two.
The tariff here for the young
very nice just the smallest hinge at the hips 78.4 from the semi-final for this dive so just see how vertical he enters the water very close to perfect but not quite and he will be penalized slightly for that with those seven and a halfs coming in
And only a 72, so that's not the start he wanted or needed.
to get into the final after the Smalling's performance and he did it but he must make sure that he's not just satisfied with that and still continues to really show what he can do at this level.
Third up is Ivan Garcia from Mexico.
Silver medalist in the ten meters synchro already with German Sanchez who missed the boat unfortunately for him.
His nickname is Polo and I saw
let's go and go he does forward four and a half somersault 3.7 big opening dive from Ivan Garcia just a really difficult dive to control the splash a little more than he might have liked nice tight tuck position spots the water the feet coming over just a little
About an 83.25 to start for Navarro.
Might miss his countryman tonight because they were chatting in the pool afterwards and keeping each other going a little bit.
But Jose Guerra, 33 year old Cuban diver.
Well, he's showing again and again that age is no barrier.
We've got a range of 17 up to 33 and he is the veteran in the field and diving beautifully.
Cuba have never won a diving medal.
He's generally regarded as their greatest ever diver.
Just made a handy start here.
76.5 just the difficulty a little low but eight and a half so you don't want less than that when the tariff is average.
Two Germans in the final 12 this evening Sasha Klein diving next is the older more experienced of the two at 26 in with three and a half somersault 3.2 tariff.
Now you like Sasha's chances, don't you, Roger?
There's an outside chance for a medal.
I think he's at the right age.
He's 26.
He's got eight European golds behind him.
He's mature.
He's experienced to this level.
He just needs to get it right.
So as a guide, 76.8 in the semi, but 80 here.
So he's off and running.
Nick McCrory is up next from the United States.
Bronze in the ten-meter synchro already in his kit back in with three and a half somersault.
Tuck's position for three point two degree of difficulty.
Oh, what an entry.
And the US cheer squad goes up.
76.8 in the semi.
Very close to the platform, which always gives us a nervous moment.
But he's got some nines here, McCrory.
And nines will be the three scores that count.
He is flying out of the blocks.
The Americans have had a good competition so far, a silver and two bronze.
Reviving those glory days when they absolutely dominated in the pool.
That eighty-six, his ten better than his score in the semi.
Well, now Victor from Russia, can he match that sort of progress?
Inward three and a half somersault, tucked three point two.
Long hold at the top, getting his composure.
Absolute silence in the pool.
well those legs folded over just a touch he collapsed into the somersault under the water to try and hold that position again he's in tight to the platform kicks out now and the legs over just a little minnaby has got a very ambitious program with three dives of three six and a three seven as well if he gets them all he could be in the medals but he may have overstretched himself anyway eighty one six to start
perfect match for his semifinal score.
Now it's Martin Wolfram from Germany his first Olympics he's just 20 he admitted that in the preliminary competition he didn't do that well because he was just so excited.
Got to keep calm now with that arm stand back double somersault two and a half twists three point six big opening dive.
Very nice.
Now this was the top scoring first round dive in the semi-final.
It drew a 91.8 for Wolfram.
Which here is not so much for his divers for the man coming up next, but it should be for this dive because he has done very well.
He's closing in on three figures with this dive.
Sneaky look at the scoreboard.
It's a 97.2.
Catch me.
That is some statement.
But he's one of only three divers to go with a high tariff first up dive and he's taken the reward for the risk.
Tom Daly has been the nation's young poster boy hero since Beijing when he was the British team's youngest member at 14 years of age.
Back two and a half somersault two and a half twist three point six of the tariff.
Tom Daly.
Well the crowd wants it to be good but he was short.
He never reached the vertical position and the replays are going to expose the error here.
They so wanted him to start with an emphatic dive but there you see he wasn't at the vertical.
The nation expects and he almost delivers.
So tough, he built through his program this morning, but he cannot afford, he can't afford many more dives like that, that's for certain.
Yeah, mid-70s won't get the job done in this company, so 75, 6, but 5 dives to try to make up for it.
Now, there's some action on the deck here, whether there was a distraction.
All right.
We've got a bit of a conversation coming on here.
Now, I'm wondering if Tom Daly.
We can only guess from here, Roger, but Tom Daly got out of the pool looking quite concerned that something hadn't gone right.
Well, there are flashes.
You see, people are asked not to have their flash on for the cameras.
They've repeated that at every session so far but haven't heard it so far this evening.
Now, it will be some controversy if they let him dive again.
Can't remember that happening in It certainly hasn't happened in these games and not in the last couple of world championships I've been to.
Now, he's come across to explain his point.
I think we've guessed it.
It's to do with the flash photography and I don't think he's got really solid ground
for a redive but it was an official protest.
Up he's going.
Well, I wonder how the rest of the field are going to react to this depending on what he does now.
I'm sure there'll be another announcement about the flash photography if that is the basis for it.
Please listen very carefully.
Tom Davies has been awarded a re-dive by FINA.
He has been awarded the re-dive because he was distracted during his dive due to the use of flash photography.
You were asked at the beginning to ensure that there was no flash photography.
Please can everybody ensure that all flashes are turned off or do not use your cameras.
Thank you very much.
Well, that was clear enough.
And Tom Daly has played.
He's got out of jail card, maybe.
Interesting to know how the rest of the competitors react to that, whether it's sympathy for a fellow pro or they think that he's got an unfair advantage.
It all depends.
How he cashes in.
So, Daley with the re-dive.
Well, seventy-five, six was what he got first time around and now the pressure's on him to get a better score than that but we saw just from one angle that there were at least half a dozen significant flashes.
What drama, hey?
Right at the first round of this competition.
Well, he is going to be handsomely rewarded for putting in the protest and rediving.
Will they pick a point on the ceiling or somewhere in the pool to orientate themselves around and that presumably is at the heart of his complaint.
The flash catches his eye and he loses his bearings in terms of spotting the ceiling and it can totally put him off.
Well he has more than cashed in on the opportunity to re-dive with a 91.8 instead of a 75.6.
And his pulse rate is up sky high.
And David Budai has had to wait his turn.
Twenty-three-year-old from Texas runs in the ten-meter synchro arm stand back double somersault two and a half twists.
Very nice from Budaya.
Only just scraped into the semifinals.
If you weren't with us last night, silver medalist at World Championships almost missed the second stage of competition, but then waltzed in in third place behind the two Chinese divers.
And he has started impressively.
Very impressively.
Silver medalist from the World Championships in Shanghai.
He's probably got the pedigree to justify being among the medal contenders.
Just another reminder for the crowd and I can't help but think, Roger, there will be plenty of people here who do not speak English and the warning may mean little to them.
Fair point.
Lin Yue.
The Chinese divers always look totally in their own zone so their concentration takes some shaking.
Inward three and a half somersault tucked for the 21 year old, the older of the two Chinese divers.
Beautiful, just what we expected.
They know how to start a competition.
They know how to win one.
And it's with this quality.
He only had eighty one point six for his first dive in the semis, but with the nines and nine and a half here.
it's going to be a very well three nine and a half so what's going to count we reject that low nine great start from him 91-2 interestingly Lin this morning after competition said he was desperate for gold and really going to be trying his best and Chubo said the medal's not so important i just want to do my best mind you he knows that his best is the best
Chubo the favorite in with three and a half somersault 3.2 his opening dive absolute silence again in here well there it is the quality that we saw from Lin replicated by Chubo don't expect him to be leading after the first round because it's a just a 3.2 tariff but he's making the most of it
Oh, there you are, a ten, just to whet your appetite for what's ahead from this man.
They keep coming back to that word consistency, but they never seem to let their standards slip.
And a 91.2.
He's picked up a couple of more points from his semifinal effort with that first dive.
So China, very solid start.
In fact, identical scores for Chu Lin
of ninety-one two.
Well, there's the standings after the first round.
David Boudia, Martin Wolfram, Tom Daly, Lin Yue, then Cubo, then McCrory.
Yet another reminder from the announcers about the flash photography.
But again, in this first round, it's the degree of difficulty, which is the deciding factor, depending on which tariff dive these competitors open up with.
It will all even itself out, of course.
Second round of six.
Wiley McCormick.
back.
Two and a half somersault.
Two and a half twists.
Three point six.
The tariff for the
those legs just folding over a little on entry he made a rip-roaring start with a fairly straightforward opening dive to be in sixth position 86.4 remember he was the last qualifier into the final but the feet just a little loss of leg form there and then over rotating so not a match in execution for his first dive
didn't make the final in Beijing.
He was sixteenth.
So, this is progress for him in his second Olympics.
What about the scores though?
Eighty-six four.
Steady eights through the middle there.
Alexander Bondar from Ukraine.
Forward
Well done.
Control the entry.
Minimize the splash.
Wasn't particularly convincing with the angle of entry.
Only just straightening out in time but the judges will like that impression of no splash.
It was eighth in the ten meter synchro competition with Alexander Gorshkova.
That's his highest tariff
Make up a little bit of ground after his first dive of seventy-two.
Ivan Garcia from Mexico.
Next to dive back three and a half somersault three point three tariff here.
It's his first Olympic Games just eighteen years of age.
From Guadalajara.
Oh, he did a great job there.
Very impressive height off the platform.
Really drove up.
Give himself time to get through the somersaults and make for an easy entry.
I like this.
Very tight tuck position.
Very good angle into the water and not much of a splash there.
So top job.
He's one of the divers who came to the World Cup event here in the Aquatic Center in February and was second in the ten meters.
So well researched for his trip.
Jose Guerra from Cuba.
33 year old back three and a half somersault
just you see these more experienced divers may not achieve that perfect vertical position and yet they can still find a way to minimize the splash and here's a prime example of it you see he was coming in at a little bit of an angle didn't throw up too much water but the judges will still have noticed that he was not quite vertical it's his fourth olympic games
He was fifth in Beijing, so he's been making steady progress.
An 88-2.
Well done to the Cuban.
Now, Sascha Klein from Germany.
Not his best opening dive.
Forward four and a half somersault with that 3.7 tariff here.
Well, by contrast with the previous dive, he had a good angle but more splash.
Now, with this dive in the semi, he scored a 90.65.
The splash might just be a handbrake on his score here.
Seven and a half's coming in.
Bronze medal in last year's World Championships in Shanghai.
So an eighty-three to five for Sasha Klein's second dive.
It's given back a few points on his semi-final score.
Nick McCrory in sixth position after his opening dive.
This one is an arm stand back double somersault with one and a half twists.
Three point two is the tariff.
Wonder how long the hole to be at the top.
It's a long hold.
You hear the gasper there, the effort as he pushes away from the platform.
That armstand's got to be held long enough and steady enough to convince the judges that you're comfortable there and in control.
Now, American has won this ten-meter platform event since the great Greg Louganis in 88 in Seoul.
He's here in London with various media duties.
Not a great score there for Macquarie.
It would have been after more than 75, too, but seven and a half and eight doesn't quite cut it in this company.
Victor Minibeyev from Russia with a forward four and a half somersault three point seven.
Already seen a few of these dives.
Completed or attempted.
Well, that's one of the better ones.
And when you're going for a 3.7 tariff, it's a real opportunity to move up the board.
An 86.95 for this one in the semi for Minnibaev.
So much rotation there.
So much spin speed they build up.
Hit the water at just over 30.
People have tried to calculate that it's knocking on towards 60 mile an hour they're spinning out but they take a bit of grasping those figures.
92.5s.
He's picked up a few points by comparison with his semi score and that's what they'll be aiming to do.
Just improve a few points every dive.
Martin Wolfram from Germany.
Terrific opening dive in with three and a half somersault just the three point two tariff here.
Oh he's done a beautiful job.
Well, Wolfram looks the man in early form with his first two dives.
Ninety-seven two for his first remember.
He's obviously made terrific progress in the last 12 months.
He didn't get through qualification at the World Championships last year, his first big event, but he is flying now.
86.4
as he had in the semi.
So Wolfram making a statement with his first two dives.
I hope that those with cameras have demobilized the flash.
Be frightened to take a photograph, wouldn't you?
Tom Daley after that dramatic re-dive now with an inward three and a half somersault.
Again, a great dive.
and he won the national under 18 title when he was only 10 and he's been a marked man or boy ever since and it's nine sir for daily a 91.8 first dive and if you're just joining us you got to retake that first dive after a protest because of flash photography in the room and he picked up 15 points on his first effort and an 86.4 here
He's on his way to something.
Even David Beckham's come to watch him then.
No more lines about diving from football.
Certainly not with Becks.
No, that never happened.
David Budaya now.
The American.
In with three and a half somersault again.
A really strong opening dive.
Well, Budaya, he was another to make a comment about that short turnaround from prelims to semis.
He only got six hours sleep, performed very well nonetheless, as he is doing in this final.
That's a spectacular second die from Budaya.
He was asked about nerves at this level of competition and said, if you ask all 12 divers whether they get nervous, 100% will say yes.
Why wouldn't you?
It's not just the competition.
It's what they're doing.
10 meters up.
They do put themselves in danger each time.
Lin Yue from China, the 2008 Olympic synchro champion.
Oh, another exquisite dive from Lin Yue.
91.2 for his first.
Starting to rack up the nines and nine and a halves consistently now.
So in control and the judges in absolute unison with their assessment of 9.5 for Linue and a 94.05.
He's the synchro specialist.
This is a rare individual opportunity for Lin.
Unlike Chubo.
Who has been the solo star, the 19 year old son of a factory worker in Sichuan province.
Armstand back, triple somersault, three point five.
That was beautiful.
This was a dive that he had a little bit of a struggle with in the semi-final.
It was only the 13th ranked dive.
He made a mistake and we were shocked to see it because we're so used to perfection or near to it from him.
But he has picked up his game here with his second attempt at it today.
This competition is really going to be tough.
Frighteningly impressive at the top and the competition just below that.
Ninety-four point five and there he is.
He's moved to normal transmission has resumed Roger.
He's number one.
Both look so calm during competition.
The status quo, Chubo Linue, David Boudin, Martin Wolfram
and through to Alexander Bonda bringing up the the rear at the moment but he's 12 out of 32.
Let's put it that way.
Let's give them the credit for reaching through to this stage which for many of them was their ambition to reach an Olympic final.
Such a fantastic occasion and they will all feel privileged to be diving alongside and in
Riley McCormick.
Canada never won a 10 metre medal.
Had nine diving medals in all.
And he's got an inward three and a half somersault to perform now.
Let's tell us this customary little flex up and down a couple of times.
Like a server bouncing the ball before smashing into the opposition court, or in this case, into the water.
And he's done a nice job there.
There's McCormick.
They must have a trigger, something that say now's the moment.
A lot of effort goes through those toes to get some elevation.
Get through the somersaults.
nice job here good tight tuck excellent position into the water and an 81.6
Steady.
I think most of us would need a trigger to get up there and the gun to go with it to jump off that ten meter board like they do.
Should never forget the the sheer bravery of it while we're admiring all the skill and all the technique.
Take some nerve.
Now, it's Alexander Bondar.
Arm stand back, double somersault, two and a half
Very tidy on the entry.
Now Bondar is about 25 points behind the leaders, so if he's to make a move, it needs to come now with dive number three, pushing up and out away from the platform, feet apart though.
I have to say probably that the entry was the best part of the dive, but his leg form a little loose, ankles not together, except for the end.
82.8 for Bondar.
Again, we must point out that we're privileged.
We see the replays of the dives.
The judges, of course, have just one shot at it to make their judgment call.
Or in Tom Daley's case, two shots at it this time.
That will be talked about, especially if he gets himself on the podium.
Ivan Garcia of Mexico.
Another 18 year old with an inward four and a half somersault.
These inward dives frighteningly close to the platform.
This is one of the toughest dives you'll see in the final.
Four point one, the tariff.
Oh, he's done a good job with it, too.
Mexican fans are happy.
He's got what could only be described as a pretty gutsy schedule for himself, isn't he?
High tariff, brave dives.
Gambler.
So the eights are going to count.
The two seven and a halfs will be rejected.
The feet just drifting away from the ideal line.
But a ninety-eight point four and that's because of that four point one tariff.
Fortune favoring the brave there with Ivan Garcia.
The very brave Jose Guerra from
That's just something to behold and remember that was as good as it can be done.
Now, it's a low tariff.
So, something in the mid-80s is is a
All right, nines are going to count.
And that's what he needs to get into that 86.4.
That's exactly what he had in the semi because he did the dive equally well there.
He's got that one under control.
Sascha Klein from Germany.
serves in the army.
Eight European titles.
Twice he's been European champion at ten metres but European championship to Olympic Games is some step up.
Arm stand back, triple somersault.
Oh and the pike position, the the legs just flipped right over and they don't want to look at the the scores but they're going to hear them.
this went rather wrong as he just straightened up too early and over it went so so the sixes are going to hurt and a 66.5 and Sasha Klein bit of a smoky for a medal but maybe not now
He was driving better earlier in the competition.
He was.
Not really been able to do it on the big stage.
Nick McCrory now from the United States.
Twenty-one years of age from North Carolina.
Forward
Tucked position, 3.7, the tariff here.
Such a hard dive to control at the end.
To achieve something like a vertical position and minimise the splash.
No one's really been able to nail this one.
High tariff, 3.7.
Big splash.
Count them if you can.
1, 2, 3, 4 and the half.
course if there wasn't a half he'd go in feet first and they just don't do that not intentionally anyway unfortunately we've not seen a disaster in this competition we've had one or two ones go terribly wrong but not a an incomplete dive which scores zero was one in the three meter competition you won't wish that on anyone victim of a reverse three and a half somersault
for the Russian diver.
First Olympic Games.
Excellent work from Victor.
The unmistakable Russian uniform worn by competitors and supporters alike.
It really lets you know that they're from that group.
He was fourth in the World Championships last year.
So again, he brings good credibility into the competition.
He hit that vertical position very early.
allowing himself to straighten out and collect an 89.1.
He's picked up 10 points on his semi-score for the same dive.
Well done, Victor Menebaev.
The last German to win a medal at 10 meters was Jan Hempel, a silver, in Atlanta in 96.
But Martin Wolfram has really put himself in with a chance here.
Reverse, three and a half somersault.
He's third.
Well, there we go.
The first little sign of pressure and a minor mistake from Martin.
I'd like to have this one back to have another crack at the entry, which is a little untidy.
Not that it was a bad position.
He just didn't control the splash as he went beneath.
There's a little art in pulling the air down with you, separating the arms, dragging it down.
And a 77-5-5 for Martin.
Tom Daly up next.
British national senior champion at 13 years.
Youngest ever European gold medallist back in 2008.
Arm stand back triple somersault.
3.5 is in fifth place.
Oh, an excellent dive from Tom Daley.
It wouldn't matter what he did, you'd get a big roar for him from this crowd, but that was worth cheering.
Great position on entry.
There's just an impression from time to time that he's not quite square.
on entry not not the line of the vertical but square with the side of the pool and.
there's a just a hint of a twist there but unless the judges spot it like we do on the slow mo it's not going to get penalized and a 92.75 that's eight marks better than from the semi we have three great dives with peter waterfield in the synchro competition you want to make sure he keeps that standard going david budai though he's also diving superbly
That was a four and a half somersault.
Tarkton, it brought a massive cheer from the American camp.
Standby, this could be close to 100.
He got 94.35 with it in the semis and this was the four and a half done beautifully.
To think he only just scraped into the semi-final, didn't he?
We nearly didn't have him in this competition and he is really scoring
99.9.
Oh, that's cruel.
Where's that extra tenth?
Business-like and up for it in his manner.
Lin Yue far more composed and restrained.
Back three and a half somersault in the silver position.
He loves this dive.
He got 102 for it in the semis, but not with that level of splash though.
So it might just hold him back a little.
Great drive off the platform.
Up and into his work.
Fantastic position.
And he's not going to score a hundred this time.
Best individual performance ever was a bronze at the 2007 World Championships.
Since then, he's really had a chance to dive individually, always in the sinker events where he's got an Olympic gold.
Almost peerless through the air.
Ninety-one point eight.
And even though it's in the 90s, he's let 11 points go from his semi score.
Let's see what all this means soon enough.
Kubo.
Reverse three and a half somersault.
The leader.
Approaching the halfway stage, this is third dive, three point three, the tariff.
Oh my goodness, what a dive.
How close was he to the platform?
We'll get another look at it to just increase your heart rate a little.
But 94.05 in the semi, his tariff for his first three dives are only 3.235 and 3.3.
And yet he's going to be at the top or near.
And his hard dives are yet to come.
and he's in second spot where those two tens oh that's tough they get ruled out as the two top scores along with the two bottom the tens don't count now he's just been displaced from the top following that wonderful 99.9 from Budaya yeah it's David Budaya who's leading at the moment he's really responding to this challenge
two, two, two, two, two, two, two, two, two, two, two, two, two, two, two, two,
Sasha Klein really starting to fade away a little bit.
I think a good thing has happened here, Roger.
Such hot favourites were Choubo and Lin Yue.
For someone to put some pressure on and actually be leading them at the halfway point could bring out yet another level from them.
I think we've got a great competition on our hands now.
Well, plenty of divers have been in position that to win the gold in Olympic Games or World Championships.
They've had to produce a series of tens.
We've got a couple in that previous round but we've not been absolutely dazzled by a score.
Brilliant, yes but there's still another level where you feel that maybe they can go.
No marks for how you get to the arm stand just as long as you hold it steadily and in good shape.
So he likes that split move to the arm stand.
Finds the water, comes in fairly vertically and gets a nice return out of the toes giving us a wave.
The director's done well to spot that, hasn't he?
Is a feature to look for in the arm stand and the camera.
He was just sixteen when he competed in Beijing.
Finished sixteenth in the ten metres but progress this time out.
Alexander Bondar from Ukraine back in eleventh position for the
Well, this is one of his better dives.
An eighty-nine one in the semi from Bondar.
And he's just failing a little to impress.
He he's not going to be a top five finisher here.
One feels on the evidence of his first four.
He was still competing at junior level last year.
Gold medalist in the European Junior Championships.
The ten meter platform.
and a bronze so far for the Mexicans in the diving pool.
He's got one of those silvers in the ten meter
If you're interested in such things, a lot of the camera angles that we're showing you are from cameras that are unmanned, if you like.
They're on cranes and tracks, controlled by technical boys outside.
Arm stand back, double somersault, two and a half twists.
And this is all human technology.
Yes, a little less than ideal at the entry.
Kicks it out well.
Looks to be getting through it OK. Nice form with the legs and then over she goes.
And that was quite a serious mistake on entry.
You'll pay for that.
All very, very good until the last gasp.
And an 81.
The judge is recognising that until he hit the water it was all done very tidily.
Jose Guerra, who was Cuba's first ever world championship medalist back in 2005 in the synchro with Aguero who didn't make the cut.
Armstand reverse triple somersault now.
Tucked position.
Three point four tariff.
Slightly hesitant armstand.
He's up there now.
And three point four the tariff.
Something in the mid to high 80s might just move him up a spot or two.
Well, the judges do like this.
Nine and a half.
may well be his last senior competition perhaps at thirty-three.
Still has to get the motivation and the training but plenty of life in the old dog yet.
Oh, that's a juicy score.
Ninety-six point nine.
Better than anything he got in the semifinal.
Class is permanent.
Sasha Klein from Germany.
Having a disappointing outing back in
Eight times the European champion.
Ah, that's better.
Absolutely ripped that entry.
They're not hiding behind their flag now.
From that effort from Sacha Klein, they're very proud of it, as he will be and should be.
Nice and tight in that pike position.
He's turning into a classic example of that consistency word again, isn't he?
Because he has shown he's got the real talent, but he just can't maintain that superb level that the Chinese divers so far have sustained.
Any of these divers in the top 12 can match the top one or two once or twice, but it's that consistency that finds them out across the six dives.
playing seventy-two holes of golf on a tournament, isn't it?
It's the it's that consistency day in, day out.
Dive in, dive out for Nick McCoury.
Reverse three and a half somersault.
He was back in ninth.
Coming into this, the fourth dive.
May not be able to improve much here as he leaps off the platform.
not yet mentioned that little bit of nice trivia about his uncle, Gordon Downey, winning a bronze for Great Britain in the Freestyle Relay back in the seventy-six Olympic Games.
Keeping up the family tradition at least by appearing in an Olympic final which is some family tradition.
We're on to Victor again from Russia who's
the fourth in the World Championships.
The current European silver medalist.
I'll stand back.
Double somersault.
Two and a half twist.
Three point six.
Great angle that.
Yes, it looked better at the top than at the bottom.
Unfortunately, from any both.
not so special from the Russian but a lot of these family connections with the previous generation having medaled.
You find this out in Olympics.
Rostovina in the artistic gymnastics who picked up a gold medal on uneven bars.
You then find out that her father was a bronze medalist in Greco-Roman wrestling.
So it often runs in families.
Russia have won ten-meter medals at three of the last four games but
Martin Wolfram just slipped back a bit.
Back three and a half somersault for the 20 year old from Dresden.
Oh, that's a bit of a crash landing, I'm sad to say, because Wolfram was having a good competition, especially with his opening couple of dives.
And it's just gone missing for him.
Confidence not there now.
short on position coming into the water and well that's counting him out a 64.8 is a disaster in a final and he may have just a mischief there with the shoulder come in at the wrong angle
Tom Daly.
Well, the public may only have discovered him four years ago, but he was on the sports radar when he was just ten and was winning the national under eighteen title, which is phenomenal.
Now, at the ripe old age of eighteen, forward four and a half somersaults, three point seven, the tariff here.
This is a a biggie for Tom Daly.
Well the crowd tells you it was very good.
I'm not convinced he was completely vertical, but I am convinced by the total lack of splash.
And the judges do like it.
They like it a lot.
And that entry was very good.
And a good tariff is going to reward him here.
And he is as well contributing to a terrific atmosphere here in the pool.
And I'm sure that the other divers, despite the waiting in the support, including Mr. Beckham, the other divers will be enjoying the atmosphere that he's generating and the scores.
That is his highest score of the competition, a 98.
David Budaya has shown that he can respond to a challenge so far.
Reverse three and a half somersault, 3.3, a slightly lower tariff for the student from Purdue University.
Oh well, yet again we're left shaking our heads to think we nearly didn't see this man in the final because his diving is right up there.
He's not worried what Tom Daley might do or how much noise he gets.
He's very much focused on his dives.
Wonderfully tight tuck.
Oh, and he's pulled a 10.
It won't count.
It's two alone.
You need three.
He's diving like a man who seems to believe that this might just be his moment.
Real conviction.
90.75.
picked up five points on his semi effort with the same.
Quietly and calmly getting on with his job of racking up these massively impressive dives.
Forward four and a half somersault tucked.
Oh short.
All right.
Now here's the little error that opens the door to the medals.
Now we've not seen this before.
He had a 94.35 in the semi with this one, but he's got a problem right here.
He was very short, bent at the hips, never got to vertical, and the judges could hardly have missed this.
This could be really costly.
It's a big deduction.
He's got two dives to try and make up for what is a 68.45, and down he tumbles.
Well, game on.
Chubo, who's even more impassive than his countrymen.
Double world champion from the world championships last year.
Back three and a half somersault.
Can be a 100-point dive for this man.
and that's what he got with it in the semi 102.6 is it that good again it's up there but maybe the splash a little bigger than we saw this morning just beautifully through the air the judges can only like that's a very vertical position
But not as good as the semi and the two fancy Chinese competitors have got a real battle on their hands to take what everyone expected would be theirs.
Well, they did say that this was China's vulnerable event, even though they lost at three meters.
and suddenly look at that David Budaya from the United States in the lead, Chubo second, Tom Daly in the bronze medal position, Jose Guerra there's quite a gap underneath Daly and Lin Yue has out to fifth.
Well, what a shock at the end of that round.
It's never over till it's over.
And maybe the pressure is even telling on the Chinese divers.
That may well be the key.
The excellence of Budaya, the growing pressure from Daley, has put the Chinese divers under unusual pressure.
Interesting to see that margin between third and fourth.
Daley with a little bit of a buffer.
21 points between him and Guerra.
And this is one lively competition we've got now with two dives to come from all 12.
And the crowd really know it.
That has really brought this aquatic centre right to its feet.
Round five of six.
Riley McCormick leads off with a reverse three and a half somersault.
Three point three the tariff.
He's diving for his own personal standings now.
Well, he kept it in nice and close to the platform that the finish didn't compliment the start.
Fix out just a little too early.
So, overcome the feet, past the vertical.
It's a shame for him.
It was very solid until the entry.
Twenty-one later this month, Riley McCormick, still pretty early in his international career.
see the analysis starts within seconds of the completion of the dive where did that not go quite as it should have alexander bonda from ukraine 12 at the moment reverse three and a half somersault oh there was a really unusual kick out there that the judges
might penalize.
The legs were on their way to straight.
He had a second thought and kicked out again.
See if you can notice here there and again almost a double pump of the knees.
Ukraine have only ever won two Olympic diving medals both of them were bronze.
The old Soviet Union had quite a tradition of course so Ukraine trying to create their own diving momentum.
The judges are just having a little bit of a struggle with that and they didn't like it and I think it was the the adjustment that he's made there from four to seven so someone's missed it and someone and a couple haven't.
A little error that we are discussing about the leg straightening.
I think he's done that to save himself and he's been penalized for it.
Even Garcia, a synchro silver medalist.
Sixth place, reverse three and a half Somersault.
Three point three, the tariff.
And a little bit behind the breakaway bunch.
well that's a great dive and it really set itself up with the tremendous height he got off the platform he really took off great power 74.25 for this one in the semis but he's through one and a half somersaults before he even passes the platform and the judges do like it he scored seven and a halfs in the semi he's pulled some nines here
He's produced some big dives as well during the three competitions.
So he's shown as well that he's got terrific talents at just eighteen.
I don't know if he wanted more, but I tell you, he's picked up fifteen points from the corresponding guy from the semi.
Jose Guerra, the senior player out there tonight at thirty-three.
Sorry to keep going on about his age, but in such a teenage sport, it is it's something he should be proud of after such a career.
Reverse three and a half somersault was his fifth dive.
Slap of the hands as he pulled himself into that tight tuck position.
Such silence in the room, it's fantastic to hear little effects that help tell the story of what's going on.
This arena which is temporarily extended out to seventeen thousand seats really has a good echo effect and reverberates around the sound which is helping create this terrific atmosphere.
Sasha Klein from Germany.
Pulled himself up a bit with a much better fourth dive.
This is a
You just know that there's better stuff in him.
A silver medalist four years ago in the 10 meter with the synchro.
And he showed enough in preliminaries and semi to suggest he could really make a challenge.
It's not quite there.
It's tough.
It's supposed to be tough and it certainly is.
77.55.
Nick McCrory might just be wondering if he can benefit from that sudden change in the top order after Lynn had that problem.
He's got a back three and a half somersault with a three point three tariff and not much room for error if he wants to keep up his scoring ratio.
He's the tallest man in the field at 180
So he certainly creates some long lines through the air, but it's about execution and nice job done by McCrory.
Pulls those long limbs through the air, the arms hands flat to create a necessary opportunity to pull the air down after him below the water.
and an eighty-four one five.
Victor Mini.
Seventh place after the fourth round.
Back three and a half somersault now with three point six.
The tariff.
A bit of strapping to give extra support on the wrists.
They do take a pounding as they enter the water.
Deep
Excellent job.
It was worth the wait, wasn't it?
Got himself set.
And he adopts a really attractive pike position here.
He's not as tight as some in terms of getting the face down onto the knees.
But elegant.
And scores on the eights.
91.8.
Well done, Victor.
Thank you.
Martin Wolfram from Germany next up.
Slip back after some terrific opening dives.
This is his biggest test in terms of level of competition.
Finding it a little tough as it goes on.
That was a back two and a half somersault, two and a half
And after his dive, he's got to deal with the din that is for Tom Daly.
He's done a nice job here, though, and a high-scoring dive for him of 88.2.
Very quickly into the twists, and then try and get the alignment right after all of that to the entry.
And that was a good effort.
Well, you can hear the cheers building.
Tom Daly is up next.
Really put himself in with a great chance in the 10 meter synchro with Peter Waterfield before the fourth dive went wrong.
But he is right in the medal frame now.
Almost a hundred with his previous dive.
This is a three point six tariff.
Back three and a half somersault piked for the 18 year old.
Oh, another good one.
He's really channeling the goodwill in the room that is all for him.
A lot of smiling faces in the Aquatic Centre as Tom Daly continues to press for a medal with some stunning dives and some ripped entries.
And like so many British athletes, he's just loving being in London.
Well it's been a great night already for Britain with Mo Farah winning the 5,000 metres just a few hundred yards away on the track and Tom Daley is on the charge.
And he's picked up another six points on his semi-final dive for the same.
So watch out.
David Boudia oozing the fact that he's now on the board and he too has got the scent of medals.
He was leading the competition after four rounds.
Must be two of the biggest dimes of his life coming up.
Back three and a half somersault.
Oh, another good one from Boudia.
Just a little too much water coming up
He's going to come under some pressure though.
Not sure if it was as good as Daley's.
And it wasn't.
He's going to slot in just behind him.
There's nothing in it.
So he's 466.05 to Daley's 466.2.
Again the commentator at the venue appealing to respect the divers, turn off the flashes and perhaps not stop the build up to Daly's dives.
Well we mentioned maybe some spectators here don't understand the instruction and there'll be some others that don't understand their camera.
Just how to turn it off.
or both.
Yeah.
Lin Yue now.
And it's all threatening to go very wrong for a twenty-one year old.
Arm stand back double somersault two and a half twists with a three point six tariff and he needs something rather special to get back in the frame.
That was better.
He might have been a little concerned about this dive that he only scored 75.6 with in the semis.
Well, he's beaten Chu in the past.
He's been a 600-plus scorer, set a record at the national championships.
This was his big day.
I just want to see these scores from the judges confirmed on the screen here.
I think there's a little bit of a range here.
Well, no, that's okay.
Eight to nine.
That's all right.
Eight and a half's count.
And Lin is behind both Daley and Budaya.
Kubo now very much a favorite.
Very much under pressure now.
forward four and a half somersault 3.7 the tariff big tariff dive so hard to control budaya did a spectacular job with his four and a half well not very sporting but the cheers i suspect are not because it's brilliant
It's a 94.35, it's a great dive but the cheers are because he's not top of the leaderboard and the British crowd is going nuts here for Tom Daly who will lead going into the final round.
I hope this temporary stand is well and truly made because the roof is threatening to go off and the unbelievable beforehand
is a possibility top of the board after round five it is the hero of Great Britain Tom Daly and look how close look at that point one five it's virtually neck and neck it's as close as you can get to a photo well what a competition this this is it's a well it's what a way to bring down the curtain unbelievable
Well, as we say back home, no more than a struck match between them.
The Beckhams are just loving it, as we all are too.
Just repeat that score.
So, Daley is ahead of Budaya and Chou Bo, who are both tied 46605 to 466.20 and then there's a gap to Lin Yue.
You would think the three medals sparring disaster are with the top three.
I can't believe those scores.
466 points is the leading score and just 0.2, less than 0.2 separating the top three divers.
Unlike in gymnastics, if they're level, share the medals.
Riley McCormack now.
It's the final round.
Back three and a half somersault.
He's in eleventh position.
Excellent.
Excellent, David.
It's hard to focus on the boys starting this sixth and final round when you know the real action is in the last three or four but this was a great dive from McCormick.
Well, he's reached the final.
He didn't manage that in Beijing.
when he was just 16 and he'll be pleased at the progress he's made.
Student from Arizona State in the United States and a good finish by the looks of it.
There it is now 95.4 and I'm wondering if he's saying where was that earlier because I really could have finished a little higher.
Well done.
Alexander Bondar now from Ukraine.
He's twelve.
Back two and a half somersault, two and a half twists for the eighteen-year-old.
I want to finish off with a good solid performance and a a feel good for what's been a brilliant competition so far.
Back two and a half somersault,
Well, just a little untidy.
We mentioned in an earlier session, he'd one day like to be the Ukraine sports minister.
Well, he sets his sights high, but that was all.
There were all sorts of problems there in execution.
The knees were bent, the ankles weren't together there.
They sort of lost the thread, really.
So it won't be a great scoring dive.
for 18 year old.
He will have his sights set on Rio.
and not quite the sign off that he was looking for.
He's peering your head to those last few dives that await us, Roger.
Tom Daly has got the least of the contenders.
So, he's really going to have to
to come out tonight and be full of it.
Forward two and a half somersault, three twists, three point eight at the end of a a bold program by Ivan Garcia of Mexico.
A couple of gold medals at the Pan American Games last year in the 10 metre platform and the synchro 10 metre.
And that silver medal in the bag for the 10 metre synchro event.
So he and the Mexicans have had a good Olympic Games in the diving pool.
Just a little pause in the judging there for Ivan and the 87.4.
So his competition concludes.
Well done to him.
Good to see the coach and the diver there, all the hard work they've all put in together.
Tom Daly, while he's going through his young mind.
Jose Guerra, first of all, has to dive back two and a half somersault, two and a half twists, 3.6.
He's in seventh place.
I'll say it one more time, the 33 year old.
Oh, wonderful finish from him.
He does already have his own slice of history for his nation with a second placing at the 05 Worlds in Montreal, Cuba's first World Championship medal, and he continues to compete at the top.
What a wonderful final dive from Guerra.
Oldest diver in the competition.
Well, what a great sign off that is.
Ninety-seven point two.
Well, I'm truly eclipsing anything he scored in the semis.
Respect is the word, I think.
Respect.
We're getting close.
Sasha Klein back two and a half somersault, two and a half
Already has an Olympic silver from Beijing in the synchro.
Back two and a half somersault, two and a half twist then three point six to conclude.
We're seeing some divers finish off their competition very nicely.
Sasha Klein just a little erratic on the finals night.
He needed six dives like that.
He might have got a different outcome, but well done to hold it together for his final dive, knowing he's out of contention.
just the scoring from the judges seems to have slowed down Roger.
I couldn't even guess why that might be but maybe the tension getting to them too knowing what's sitting in front of them trying to separate three divers with 0.15 between them.
I want to make sure they get it right or as right as you can do in what is a subjective sport after all.
Now Nick McCrory from the United States 21 year old
Sixth in the World Championships last year.
Ninth going into this final dive.
Oh, and another excellent final dive from one of our finalists, Mick McCrory.
Well done.
Maybe the whole occasion, the drama, the crowd, the atmosphere is getting to all of them, wanting them to put on a real show, a special night.
He did score a 90 for this dive in the semis.
and a ninety-seven point two.
Well, that speaks to their endurance and concentration that they can pull out another big dive to finish it off.
victim in the five fifth place back to a half somersault two and a half twist out of the middle frame but he's had a good competition in his first Olympic games.
The twenty-one year old.
Certainly not short of high tariff dives.
He brings to the
and yet another top dive.
Mini Bayer's last three dives are all 3.6 and his second is a 3.7.
Sets the bar high and he has cleared it easily here in style.
A sense of anticipation around this pool as we get nearer to these crucial final dives.
And a 91.8 for Victor brings a smile as he finishes his Olympic campaign.
I just hope the crowd has some appreciation of what a difference the degree of difficulty is going to make for Tom Daly.
He's jumping into the water with a 3.3 and the others 3.6.
Martin Wolfram, eighth place going into this final dive, which is a forward four and a half somersault with a three point seven tariff in his first Olympic Games.
Oh, he's got that shoulder issue.
He's not even paddling with that arm.
I hope he hasn't done something serious here.
And I think he has.
He looks in pain.
He is struggling.
He is in trouble.
And this is most concerning.
I hope he hasn't suffered a little dislocation there.
He's managed to get himself up onto the pool edge.
Oh, that looks like a dislocation to me.
What a way to end.
I hope that's not the case, but he's in trouble.
I'll just try and keep that stabilized, but I don't like the way that it's hanging.
Yes.
There's a little bone pointing the way it should not.
So that is the danger of this sport.
Now.
Now we come down to what it's all about.
If we didn't have enough drama, we've got an injury and now a nation hoping that Tom Daly can produce something special.
The biggest two seconds of his life ahead of him, Tom Daly.
leading in gold medal position his final dive just at 3.3 tariff on a reverse three and a half somersault but he is diving for gold must extract maximum value from this one silence oh it's good it's better than good they're on their feet they love him
He knows it's good.
I think he's relishing in the reception too.
He's laid down the challenge.
You beat me if you're good enough.
And last we see that Daily Smile.
Oh, cometh the moment.
Maybe come with Tom Daley.
90.75.
He's just beaten his score from the semi when he also had some nines in there.
This was beautiful.
Tight tuck.
Look at the finish here.
Absolutely vertical by the time he hits the water.
The splash is barely there.
And he is richly rewarded.
But hold on, folks, because there's some tough dives with bigger difficulty coming.
He knows though that he has put on the big show and he will be delighted at that.
And the young lad comes through for the first time rather than the more introverted figure in competition.
Now, David Budaya has responded to every challenge.
A mature American diver now.
This he will believe is his moment.
Three point six his tariff.
We've got to emphasize that.
Back two and a half somersault, two and a half twist.
Oh, it's good too.
And Tom Daly's got to be concerned about that.
It only needs to beat him by one point and he's out of the gold medal position.
And Budaya waits and hopes.
What a competition he's put together.
24 hours ago, he was nearly out of it.
He's relaxed.
He said he relaxed and he's been enjoying it.
And this is nail biting.
Oh!
He's there.
Oh, he's more than there, 102.6.
He has stormed to top position.
Oh, what a moment for this man, a career highlight.
But it's not over yet.
It's still the favorite to go, not to mention Lin Yue.
Only one diver in the last three games from China has missed out on a 10 meter medal.
So he will be feeling in this rare opportunity to compete individually that he has missed the boat.
Back two and a half somersault, two and a half twists.
It's not good enough.
There was a separation of the ankles.
The entry wasn't quite right.
And it's not quite good enough, I would feel.
And I'd leave it to the judges.
But uncharacteristically, the ankles not locked together.
The splash, too big.
The chance for medals.
They're not used to it.
Chen Raolin.
The women's champion we saw down there on the bench.
They're all out there supporting.
They came here for the clean sweep of eight golds.
They're looking for seven.
They may have to settle for six.
Tom Daly knows he's got a medal.
It's just what color.
So does Budaya.
Because there's just one man to come.
You can see the pressure just lifted off Tom Daley.
That re-dive, that opening re-dive, well, Chubo, the pre-race favorite, as it were, back two and a half somersault, two and a half twist, the last dive of these Olympic Games.
What a competition.
Well, it was good, but is it a hundred dive?
Budaya might be the man.
Choubo lost that 2009 World Championships to Tom Daley right in the final dive.
He knows what it's like.
Just not quite perfect with the entry.
There was a bigger splash than we're used to seeing from this man.
Through the air, beautiful.
The finish, not the very best impression he could leave.
He wants to see what this is.
And he's forced his way between Badaer and Daley.
So Budaya is your champion.
David Budaya of America follows in the great tradition, the great days are back for American diving and the Chinese have to settle for second place with Chubo, the favorite.
Tom Daly gets the bronze.
A brilliant, dramatic, staggering competition and David Budaya comes out of the pool on top of the world.
Well, it's a competition that anyone who's seen it here or at home will remember for many a day.
We've had all sorts of drama here, but Chu Bo is crushed by coming up short.
Coming up short to 9.509, and that is not enough.
And Tom Daley knows how tough it is to get a medal in this 10-metre platform diving event.
And he is the first Briton since Brian Phelps back in 1960, 52 years ago.
And David Butaya.
bringing the good times back to diving in the United States.
Sun Bo has to settle.
Steve, your thoughts?
Well, I'm just staggered at Budaya's competition.
You know, last night he was inconsistent, he was all over the place, he fell into the semi-final.
Then he impressed us, Budaya, by qualifying in third best position and now he's won it.
And that top score of 102.6 for his final dive just blew them away.
And Chou Bow, five dives in the 90 and a 100, not good enough.
That tells you how good Bodaya was.
And Tom Daly has thrilled this British crowd.
I just feel privileged to be sitting here to have seen it and to have enjoyed it and to watch these men under pressure perform.
so exciting and you experience this for a massive crowd not used to big crowds in diving events in this country and they have seen something quite unforgettable
and never presume it's over.
Chubo a tearful figure.
He has had his success.
David Boudia, 23 year old from Abilene in Texas will feel that he has worked for this and he's worked for this over three sessions.
It's in there sharing the tears.
They win together and lose
The stars and stripes are getting ready to be unfurled and hang high.
A great respect from all the divers.
They know this has been a great competition.
Well, they were expected to and Lynn to take the top two places, but there's only room for one of them on the podium and it'll be a silver medal.
And Budaya has come from 10th four years ago to first in London.
It's been a long journey and a very successful and happy one for him now.
He's dominated at home in the States, 16 national titles.
He's won.
And the United States, this is their 129th diving medal.
They used to dominate before the Chinese entered the games and then stole their show.
But now this will mean so much to them to be back on top of the platform.
And we know about David that originally with this discipline, he was scared of heights.
He had some work done with the sports psychologist.
He now describes it as a walk in the park.
Well, wherever he walks now, he's going to be recognized as a gold medalist and someone who won a most extraordinary competition here.
And by less than two points from Chubo and Tom Daly, ten behind Chubo, but well clear a victim in a bay of an absolutely worthy medalist.
Oh, my goodness.
What a competition, Roger.
Lin Yue will be distraught.
Their expectations and the pressure on them is so high.
And for many of these divers, their time will come again, just teenagers, half the field remember, it was their first Olympic Games.
And the great Greg Luganis being introduced to the crowd, the real idol of American diving, an iconic figure, and he, more than anyone, will be delighted to see an American right at the top of diving's Blue Ribbon event.
Such a buzz in this place as well.
You don't have to know a lot about diving to know you've been at something special.
Now Louganis a winner of this event in Los Angeles and Seoul.
Klaus Diabasi of Italy won it three in a row.
and the British team all in there.
They know what pressure Tom's been under.
Of course, his father died and he'd been such a support and a presence to him.
He'd been bullied at school all his life seems to be played out in a public spotlight but
And let's go back again to that first dive where he was distracted by camera flashes in the crowd.
He was given a 75.6 wisely.
He and his coach appealed.
Fina took a sympathetic view.
He redived and went from 75.6 to 91.2 and that proved absolutely crucial.
It took some nerve to do that, to have the professionalism to say that.
It's all history now.
Actually, when you look at the margin between third and fourth, it was more than the 15 points.
In the end, there won't be any protests from those beneath him because he was so clearly in third place.
And that's of some comfort, I think, to anyone who might have wanted to question whether he should have been allowed to re-dive because the margin made sure it wasn't an issue in the end.
But it did have a massive effect on his confidence.
Absolutely, yeah.
Put him in contention and ask questions of Baddaya and Choubo.
And he's getting all the coverage here because of his special place in the British consciousness.
He and Jessica Ennis were the two poster boy and girl.
He will feel as though he's got his gold really by being on that podium.
David Budaya though will take all the plaudits and Chubo with an Olympic silver medal almost feeling like the
Yes, well I think the weight of expectation was well and truly on his shoulders and he and he simply didn't dive quite as well as he did in the semis.
It's about delivering when the medals are on offer.
Those earlier scores of course don't carry forward to the final and Padaya saves his best when it matters.
Bronze and silver his haul from these
Olympic Games.
The World Championships are in Barcelona for swimming next year when these divers will recongregate.
They will have to be right at their very best to match a show like this but it's that Olympic title that is the big one.
That's what makes you a diving
So we won't be far away from a medal presentation, and nearly everyone is staying for it.
And so are we.
I've been impressed with the way crowds have stayed.
You know, the extra minutes to, even if there's been no British competitor on the day, I did a lot of sessions of gymnastics and observed that that was the case every time.
And that makes a difference to the athletes, Roger.
well the pool it has to be said was hopelessly one-sided in its support but within that there was still a full emotional range throughout the three sessions of the diving for those divers who really performed brilliantly and those who may be disappointed one's got to say that those slightly disappointing marks for the top guys in the last round or two were
Fairly enthusiastically received by the crowd but in general the atmosphere has been very special and it's another successful competition in these London 2012 games.
Walking to the Aquatic Centre across the Olympic Park past the stadium this evening.
The atmosphere around it was a glorious summer's evening and you can't always say that in Stratford even in August and the atmosphere was great.
every different country was mixing.
There were loads of Dutch fans going to see the hockey.
Everybody's streaming there with their colors and the atmosphere was absolutely special as it has been throughout two weeks and for everybody lucky enough to get a ticket in here tonight then this competition and the drama and the excitement of it all and a happy enough ending for the crowd has really topped it off.
It's been special.
Yeah and when you enjoy an evening like tonight outside especially as you say Roger you realize you just blow away all your cynicism about the Olympics whatever that those cynicisms might be and rejoice in the human spirit that's and the goodness that's out there and the happiness that it generates on a night like tonight when it's just a great fun to be around Olympic Park.
This is what it's all about.
When you bring an Olympics to a city, you hope to capture that and it's been done here, that's for sure.
And a big contributor to that every time when it works is the volunteers.
The quality and the attitude of the volunteers.
I've been really impressed.
I've been lucky enough to attend six Olympics and no one's done it better than here in terms of making everyone from overseas and locally feel so welcome.
Well, that's terrific to hear.
I've been around quite a few different events during the last two weeks.
Not all have been gold medal events, but weightlifting and rowing, a real range of sports, handball even, and the arena's been packed out and you get supporters turning up watching sports they know nothing about and people they know nothing about and paying quite a bit of money for it and just being delighted to be there and be a part of it.
If you're just joining us we're awaiting the medal presentation for the 10 meter platform.
A quite sensational evening of competition.
Tinged with a little bit of drama and sadness for the injury to Martin Wolfram with the what we suspect was a shoulder dislocation on his last dive.
the word about the Chinese divers as well because the standards they've set and the way that they have hauled the sport forwards with their exemplary performances in no way is it decrying their efforts because people are almost celebrating that they've been beaten it's a it is a backhanded compliment here in that way that they've set their standards so high but it does prove that nobody wins all the time every time
And what it proves too is that in the last round pressure puts a microscope on your ability to cope with what's happening and sometimes you can just expose a weakness that maybe you can deal with in years to come once you've had the experience of dealing with it.
I think that's what David Badaar in particular did because he was following Tom Daley, the crowd were really up, the Chinese were next and he always seemed to respond and kept that pressure on the two Chinese divers and to some extent, to two different extents, they did crack.
Now we're ready for that victory ceremony which will be raucously supported
from all quarters.
They are really going to enjoy the next 10 minutes.
We've got two very happy men and a slightly disconsolate Choubo.
He really expected to win.
His country expected him to, but any competitor should be proud and pleased to receive silver.
You're feeling that in golden bronze, they're really going to enjoy this.
And he was vice president of the Beijing Games organizing committee for six years.
He might just have been expecting to present a gold medal to one of his countrymen.
President of FINA, Dr. Julio Cesar Malione, who is from Uruguay, presents the flowers.
Tom Bailey can't get up on that platform quick enough.
The first 10-meter medal for Great Britain since 1960.
52 years.
Just listen to this.
Every mum throughout the land would be saying, ah, bless him, won't they?
Yeah, that's a smile that you'll see across newspapers across the world.
He's got to be a hard man not to really have your heart go out to him what he's been through and he'll be thinking of his late father in this moment, I'm absolutely sure.
He's got to be one of the happiest bronze medals of the games.
I think so, and you can see the gesture to the crowd that is saying, yes, thank you for your support, this is for you too.
For Chubo, more dazzling skills, but just for once, the world champion has to miss out.
Well, that's the unpredictability of sport.
The hottest of favorites coming in.
But he didn't reckon, perhaps, on the performance of David Budaya.
He chose his moment to produce an outstanding evening's competition.
And a bit of a smile at last from the 19 year old and the gracious bow from all the Chinese divers as ever.
But it takes a great diver to win a great competition.
And the gold medalist is from the United States.
The good days are rolling again for diving in the States.
David Budai wins the gold.
to think that less than two tenths of a point separated the top three divers coming into that last round he held his nerve he pulled out a 102.6 to win it and to win it by a couple of points well done David and his experience having been to a games before maybe that helped him and we'll say it one final time he nearly didn't even make the semi-final
The United States of America.
I'm sorry.
You can hardly believe it.
I just want to shoot you the ranking of where he was after each series of dives.
Equal first after the first, equal third, first, first, equal second, and first.
He was the most consistent man.
We talked about quality and consistency at the start.
David Badaia delivered it, and he's been delivered a gold medal.
Nobody's going.
Nobody's gone for the early bus, have they?
No.
And Chubo was only in front after the second series of dives.
Equal fourth after the first, then first, second, second, second, second.
Never quite cracked it.
Well, they will pose for the photographs now and enjoy the moment.
I think Tom Daley is going to do his own victory lap in front of all these supporters.
Now they can take the photographs and use their flash guns as much as they want.
Now he's going up into the crowd there.
He's going to make the most of this moment.
He's trying to steal the show.
David Budayev doesn't mind.
He's got the gold.
They're really supposed to march around together so that the photographers can get the shot of the three of them together.
But David Budaya has been thrown the stars and stripes.
That's all good.
We're nearly at the end of the journey, aren't we, Roger?
And there's a sense of almost melancholy and sadness that this great party is coming to an end.
They're going to celebrate as well.
There is a great camaraderie, one senses, between the divers.
Great stuff.
Just enjoy these scenes there.
Moments to cherish.
I hope Chubo also realizes the part he played and what a contribution he's made to 10 meter platform diving and just throw in here too Roger that you don't get a wonderful competition like this unless you've got three or four guys competing at the very top providing you with real drama it's not really as exciting if one man races away with it
to have Chubo and Tom Daly there pushing Budair all the way and to get the surprise result.
This is one of the great competitions you'll see in diving.
You need more than one man to be standing up and giving you a story.
So a great competition for the United States.
who got off to a good start with David Budaya winning bronze in that 10 meter synchro and it gave the rest of the American diving team a bit of momentum.
He started it and boy has he finished it.
Six out of eight then for Chinese diving.
three meters and ten meters for men let it down and when you set your standard so high you can understand disappointment with silver but Tom Daly pretty happy with bronze to say the least
Well, the blow torch of Olympic competition shows the strengths and frailties of the athlete.
We saw all of that tonight and we've come away with a wonderful feeling about the health of the sport.
The competitors who give us the pleasure from it and just delighted to have been here.
United States got a silver in the women's three-meter synchro and a couple of bronze in the men's three-meter synchro as well with Ipsen, Jumei, and Johnston and Bryant getting that women's silver.
So, a gold, a silver and two bronze for the United States.
Well, this party's going to carry on for quite some time.
Steve, thank you very much for your contribution as we confirm the final result and some dazzling statistical work, if I might say so.
For an artistic sport, you can certainly crunch a few numbers.
Well, the statistics are also important, aren't they?
When you're looking at degrees of difficulty and execution, the number that really matters is the man who's on top at the end, and David Badiah.
particularly with that 102 last dive to produce that under pressure, reminiscent in some ways of the finish in Beijing four years ago.
Remember some of those names down the bottom end, just teenagers in their first Olympic Games.
They will be competing, but the standard is set so high.
Now the end of a couple of astonishing weeks of great competition in this aquatic center.
Seventeen thousand capacity and boy have they all had their moneys worth.
A great competition here in the ten meter platform diving.
And I think there's a bit of a party going to be happening in the United States camp and also in the British camp.
If you're scared of heights, look away now as we take you to the edge of the platform and consider what the competitors had six times over.
And before you worry, that is an automatic suspended camera.
There's not some poor chap holding that one.
But again, just to recap here, it was an American gold, a Chinese silver, and a very British bronze here in the 10 meter platform.
Leave you just to enjoy these final few memories from this great night of competition.
We certainly hope you've enjoyed it.
Hard to remember it all, but I'm sure you'll remember some of it and especially the end and the joy of victory for Badiah and bronze for Daley.
A great night off the platform and it was again just our pleasure to bring it to you.
you